Contact

contact@gaboesquivel.com

www.linkedin.com/in/gaboesquivel (LinkedIn)

gaboesquivel.com/about (Personal) github.com/gaboesquivel (Other) stackoverflow.com/story/ gaboesquivel (Portfolio)

Top Skills

DeFi

GraphQL

TypeScript

Languages

Spanish (Native or Bilingual)

English (Full Professional)

Italian (Professional Working)

Portuguese (Professional Working)

Gabo Esquivel

Software Architect

San Jose, Costa Rica

Summary

I'm a full-stack software engineer with over 15 years of experience, specializing in web3 technologies since 2017. My background includes work on numerous blockchain projects, a decade with NodeJS and cloud platforms, as well as advanced expertise in containers, React, and TypeScript.

Learn more on my website gaboesquivel.com

Experience

bitcashBank Software Architect January 2020 - Present (3 years 10 months)

Buy, Trade, Deposit & Earn High Yield on Crypto. Bitcash allows you to exchange your money with others for local currency stablecoins or bitUSD. You can then trade bitUSD for Bitcoin, Ethereum, USDT, or smaller coins like Grin. BitcashDAO allows members to participate and make decisions.

At Bitcash, I joined the team at its inception, overseeing critical aspects of the platform's growth. As the platform evolved, I transitioned into a consulting role, offering ongoing support to ensure Bitcash's continued success.

Responsibilities included:

- Software architecture design and infrastructure management.
- Development of smart contracts and user interfaces.
- Tech recruitment and developer training.

Antelope, EVM, WebAuthN, React, Docker, Cloud, Node, GraphQL, Postgres, TypeScript

gaboesquivel.com
Software Engineer
July 2008 - Present (15 years 4 months)

I help companies develop software products and make technical decisions, collaborating with stakeholders and developers in the design and implementation of software applications, taking ideas from conception to production and ensuring successful execution.

My primary focus lies at the crossroads of emerging technologies, financial services, and delivering exceptional user experiences.

Spoken languages: English, Spanish, Portuguese, and Italian.

Blockchain, DeFi, NodeJS, Databases, Linux, Docker, Cloud, GraphQL, React, React Native, TypeScript

ZTX

Software Engineer August 2022 - April 2023 (9 months)

Metaverse

ZTX is a web3 metaverse platform empowering creators and communities to build, play and earn. Founded in 2022, ZTX is the blockchain initiative backed by Jump Crypto and ZEPETO — the largest metaverse in Asia with over 400 million lifetime users.

I joined as a contractor during its early stages. My key contributions involved:

- NextJS architecture for the avatar builder.
- Establishing a bridge between WebGL, Wallets, and EVM.
- Integration of backend services and analytics.

WebGL, Ethereum, Ethers, AWS, Node, React, Next

RareMint

Software Engineer

October 2021 - December 2022 (1 year 3 months)

Metaverse

RareMint offers authentic real-world sports collectible assets and creates a digital experience of those collectibles through asset-backed NFTs.

Contributions:

- Maintaining the NFT marketplace and data indexer.
- Optimizing responsiveness and reducing load times.
- Supporting the first auctions on the Polygon network.

Ethereum, Polygon, Ethers, React, Docker, GCloud, Node, GraphQL, TypeScript

Tractor Supply Company Software Consultant July 2020 - December 2020 (6 months)

I consulted on the Tractor Supply React Native app, where I:

- Evaluated and assessed architectural designs.
- Suggested enhancements for performance, code quality, and workflows.
- Created an augmented reality feature for users to visualize outdoor products on their premises.

React Native, React, Containers, Cloud, Node, TypeScript, Augmented Reality

Emanate

Software Engineer December 2019 - July 2020 (8 months)

Emanate is a network marketplace built for music lovers and creators. Powered by immediate payments and automated technology, Emanate connects players in the music industry in a way never before seen. Powered by Web3 technology, the platform manages the entire journey of music creation, distribution, promotion, and monetization

Contributions:

- Maintaining the web app streaming platform.
- Creating the artist's back office for revenue distribution.
- Integrating with EOS mainnet and AWS services.

Blockchain, React, TypeScript, EOSIO, AWS

Make Sense Labs Inc Software Engineer July 2019 - December 2019 (6 months)

A blockchain technology and DeFi company building consumer products through tokenized systems and incentives. Sense.chat allows you to safely chat and transact with your friends and family without your data being stored or spied on by third-parties.

Tasks involved:

- Crafting chat and wallet functionalities.
- Enhancing React Native app efficiency.
- Integration with EOS mainnet.

React Native, TypeScript, EOSIO

EOS Costa Rica Software Architect May 2018 - July 2019 (1 year 3 months) Costa Rica

EOS Costa Rica provides infrastructure for EOSIO blockchains, enterprise solutions and custom smart contract development.

Contributions:

- EOS mainnet launch and validator management.
- Setting up a custom private blockchain for Grant Thornton.
- Architecting EOS Rate and InterX React frontends.
- Tech recruitment and developer training.

EOSIO, Smart Contracts, Postgres, Docker, Azure, Node, GraphQL, React

Knowledge.io
Software Architect
September 2017 - May 2018 (9 months)

Knowledge rewards people for what they know and how much they know and gives people the opportunity to be recognized and compensated for sharing this information.

Responsibilities:

- Leading token development for a successful ICO.
- Building and leading a development team.
- Architecting a marketplace and wallet dashboard.
- Software design and scrum management.

Ethereum, AWS, Serverless, GraphQL, ReactNative, React, Node.js, Infra-as-Code, Jenkins

Wink Lead Architect May 2016 - September 2017 (1 year 5 months)

Costa Rica

Wink marked a pioneering milestone as Costa Rica's first neo-bank, introducing a mobile app that empowers users to conduct their banking activities seamlessly online, eliminating the necessity for physical branch visits.

My contributions:

- Led the development of the initial mobile app and backend services on AWS.
- Collaborated closely with our partner bank for seamless API integration.
- Implemented security protocols and ensured regulatory compliance.
- Assembled a dedicated six-member team to bolster our objectives.

Serverless, ReactNative, React, NodeJS, Infra-as-Code, Zero-Trust, Biometrics, Mocha, Chai

MyPhoto.com

Technical Lead

April 2015 - May 2016 (1 year 2 months)

MyPhoto.com is an online platform that turns digital photos into personalized keepsakes. Users can upload images and create custom products like canvas prints and photo books, making it simple to transform memories into meaningful gifts or décor items.

Contributions:

- Shaping technical vision and scrum management.
- Creating backend services for e-commerce.
- Optimizing the user experience.

React, Node, Hapi, Swagger, Redux, AWS, Docker, Jenkins, Postgres, Linux

18Techs

Software Engineer

September 2013 - April 2015 (1 year 8 months)

As a Fullstack software engineer, I led the development of web and hybrid mobile apps, including the creation of the 4Tius, a platform that streamlines fitness data monitoring.

My contributions:

- Developing backend APIs for data capture and refinement.
- Designing a user-centric dashboard.

- Crafting a tailored back office.

Node.js, Express, AWS, Linux, MongoDB, Angular.js

Possible Worldwide UI Lead March 2012 - September 2013 (1 year 7 months)

Costa Rica

Possible Worldwide, under WPP Digital, is a global digital marketing and design agency. I joined the team for a significant AMC Networks project. The application allows you to watch movies online on facebook and get detailed information about the directors, actors, and the making of the film, make lists of favorite scenes, vote, and share with your friends.

Contributions:

- Architecting and developing the frontend.
- Leading a five-member developer team.
- Creating a back-office for game development.
- Integrating with Brightcove, Facebook, and custom APIs.

JavaScript, PHP, CSS, Facebook API

American Express

UI Engineer

April 2010 - March 2012 (2 years)

The American Express website offers credit card information and financial services.

Responsibilities included:

- Migration from DoJo to jQuery.
- Responsive Layouts, A/B Testing and Analytics.
- Integration with AMEX backend.
- Development of Credit Cards management module.

JavaScript, CSS, Java

InterGraphicDESIGNS
Web Developer
July 2008 - April 2010 (1 year 10 months)

Development of custom wordpress sites and modules for a proprietary CMS (php, ajax)

JavaScript, PHP, AJAX, Wordpress

Hewlett-Packard Technical Support August 2007 - July 2008 (1 year)

English and Portuguese(Brazil) Technical Support for HP employees.

Education

Universidad Cenfotec

Bachelor of Science (BS), Software Engineering · (2006 - 2009)